<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons cry ascended to God, and entred into the hearts, and eares of men for reuenge of bloodshedders, burglaiers, and vagabounds. Manifested the last sessions, holden at Iustice Hall in the old Baily the 9. 10. 11. 12. of December, Anno Dom. 1619. Likewise heerein is related, the courts legall proceedings, against the malefactors that were executed at Tiburne and about London, and the chiefest offenders, there offences and confessions at large expressed.</title>
            <author>Goodcole, Henry, 1586-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853589</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1101:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons cry ascended to God, and entred into the hearts, and eares of men for reuenge of bloodshedders, burglaiers, and vagabounds. Manifested the last sessions, holden at Iustice Hall in the old Baily the 9. 10. 11. 12. of December, Anno Dom. 1619. Likewise heerein is related, the courts legall proceedings, against the malefactors that were executed at Tiburne and about London, and the chiefest offenders, there offences and confessions at large expressed.</title>
                  <author>Goodcole, Henry, 1586-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Barnard Alsop, and are to be solde at his house by Saint Annes Church neere Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Henry Goodcole.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-C4).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page cropped, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crime --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Criminals --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:1"/>
            <p>LONDONS CRY: ASCENDED TO GOD, AND entred into the hearts, and
eares of men for Reuenge of Bloodſhedders, Burglaiers, and Vagabounds.</p>
            <p>MANIFESTED THE LAST SESSIONS, holden at Iuſtice Hall in the old
Baily the 9. 10. 11. 12. of December, Anno Dom. 1619.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe heerein is related, the Courts legall proceedings,
againſt the Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that were executed at Tiburne and about London, and
the chiefeſt Offenders, there Offences and confeſsions at large
expreſſed.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a man hanged on gallows</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Barnard Alſop,</hi> and are to ſolde
at his Houſe by Saint Annes Church neare Alderſgate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1620</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE DESCEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and Generous Knight Sir <hi>Edward
Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neile,</hi> increaſe of Grace, Honour, and fauour with God and
men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, our moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious, gracious
Soueraigne Lord &amp; King, in that his moſt ioy all Title, of King of great
Brittain, France, and Ireland, rancketh in the forefront thereof (God, and Gods
grace) by it his anoynted elected King, and our Supreme head and gouernour, in
lieu vnto God for thus anoynting him with the oyle of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, aboue all
that he hath no fellowes, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſo high, that all the people to
him, as vnto God, ſhall bend, kneele, obey, and fulfill his Royall will, and
obſerue his Lawes, and Statutes, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to the whole world
profeſſeth publickely, to honour, ſerue, and to ſet foorth the praiſe
of this God, who hath ſo honored him: he writes himſelfe therefore, <hi>A
defender of the Faith, and a maintainer of his Truth.</hi> Oppoſing all the
Enemies of the ſame by ſword, word, and pen, and nothing more doth his
moſt royall heart delight in, and with any to be conuerſant, then with the
moſt Reuerend Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops and others thereof to diſpute, and
with <hi>Dauids</hi> Bleſſed man day and night, to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed therein,
ſollacing his ſoule with that ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing greene paſtures of
Scriptures, when as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were paſſing there time in ſports in giuing
content to the fleſh, yet his Maieſty to the ſoule,
<pb facs="tcp:18979:3"/> witnes that moſt learned and godly Booke of the
Lords prayer, written by his Maieſtie the laſt Chriſtmas. Such a moſt
bleſſed Lord and King, I hope ſuch attendants, that affect Gods honour
and ſeruice, &amp; preſeruation of there country where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they liue.</p>
            <p>Amongſt many of thoſe Honorable, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull attendants
on that moſt ſacred perſon of his Maieſtie. I humbly attend you noble
Sir, to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize like your good Maiſter Truth. There hath beene many
vntruths diunlgd in the world of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, that ſhould come this
Seſſions, ſuch as a Chaundler, that ſhould lend money, and them to whom
he lent it, by the high way to robbe them of it againe. Likewiſe a ſpeach
of an Inholder at Saint Albons which ſhould Robbe, and kill his Gueſts in
London highwayes all which, your Worſhippe knowes right well to be moſt
groſſe vntruths. To giue the world ſatisfaction I haue haſtily written
this ſmall Pamphlet, wherein is nothing but truth, your ſelfe being an eye,
and eare witnes being, on the Bench a Commiſſioner in London: I humbly
craue pardon at your Worſhips hands, for what in this ſhall ſeeme
amiſſe to your learned Iudgement by Gods grace I hope ere long in another
nature, to your vewe ſhall be preſented to be amended vouchſafe your kind
acceptance, and Patronage of this for this time, and I will reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>At your ſeruice,</hi> Henry
Goodcole.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:3"/>
            <head>LONDONS CRY FOR REVENGE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Awe is the principall foundation, (whereon the welfare of euery
good man conſiſteth and dependeth, and true execution, the life of the
ſame, without which, no peace or ſafety, can bee either vnto the Church or
Common-wealth: but Iniquity would in a moſt high nature flouriſh, yea, to
the vtter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpating of all the godly, and vertuous were they not by them
ſuppreſt, who are the true Contradicters, and oppoſers thereof. Whithin
the bounds and lymites of Lawe, the perſon, goods, lands, houſes, chattels,
and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, are confined, and vnder the wings of the ſame
ſheltred, thether to fly for redreſſe againſt all the outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and
wilfull violaters of the ſame. Therefore by all Chriſtian Kings, and
Princes, Statuts &amp; penall lawes, were conceiued, and enacted, <hi>debellare
ſuperbos, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſubiectis,</hi> to ſubdue, and ſubiect
enormious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and to patronize ſubmiſſe and humble minded good
Chriſtians, whoſe protection, and preſeruation of life, ſtate, and
perſon: wholeſome and good lawes, doe as with a hedge inuiron, and
incloſe all the exclude all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders into any of the leaſt liſts or
limits. Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:18979:4"/> Kings and Princes, whom none but God alone maketh
chiefe and electeth to beare rule ouer his people, it hath pleaſed him to
ſtile them with this moſt glorious Title: I ſayd yee are as gods, all men
whatſoeuer, ſhall honour, feare, and obey you: and as gods heere on earth
yee ſhall behaue your ſelues in your Royall authority from me deriued
(ſaue and deſtroy) ſpare and puniſh, honour and diſhonour, exalt the
vertuous, and loue them for there vertuous integrity, and rebuke ſhame and
confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on put to the wicked. And in them there is an externall Maieſtie,
whereon ſtedfaſtly looking, it ſtricketh terror and amaſement to the
heart) ſtupidity to the ſences, as not daring to behold the glorious
luſter of that bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; reaſon, valour, fortitude, ſtrength,
vnderſtanding, all with <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſonne ſtanding ſtill in the
valley of <hi>Aia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and like a Gyant refreſhed at there command
ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly running.</p>
            <p>There ſhining glorious faces, are like the Sunne in a mans eyes,
which at the firſt much dazeleth them: but with vſe and continuance, they
can the better, and ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner lookt thereon.</p>
            <p>Behold, it hath reſemblance to God, whom for to ſee, to
fleſh and blood, nothing more intollerable, yet moſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially terrible
to the wicked and vngodly: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous neclectors of his will, rebels to
his Lawes, Malefactors dares not behold the face, nor cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare
ſpeake of a priuate Magiſtrate, which is in them apart, and little
glimmering light of that Deity: theſe ſecondary meanes are ſubordinate,
like the Moone, and Starres, from the glorious Sunne: namely doe receiue light,
and heate from thence. Reuerend Iudges, and Magiſtrates, doe ſhinne in
there kind expound the Lawe, and to ſpeake vnto the people, in truth equitie
and vprightnes. They as from a liuing ſpring deriue there ſweete
iſſuing ſtreames, which doe runne through out all the parts, and coaſts
of this Kingdome, to giue each there refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:18979:4"/> in due time and ſeaſon, namely vnto the
oppreſſed, to yeild remedy and redreſſe, and vnto the fatherleſſe,
and friendleſſe, to be a ſure refuge, in the time of there troubles, that
great and vild mightines, may not get the vpper hand of the vertuous, to
trample them vnder there feete. The Sunne is no whit abaſed, though his
radient Beames be ſplendeth on the ſtincking dunghill, as well as on the
ſweeteſt flower on the Garden, to each according to nature, hee extracteth,
and good or bad, neyſome or wholeſome ſents, diſperſeth. Though the
Sunne ſhinne, on the bad as well as the good, on that which is loathſome,
as well as oderiferous is the inſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereon, any way there vnto
preiudicious no whit at all, for euery thing whereunto the heate thereof
exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, it cheriſheth, making it to yeald foorth the fruit, in dead time,
ſeaſon, and place, Becauſe where the corne groweth, and by the Sunne is
rypened, the Cockle doth likewiſe proſper, is that in the Sunne, or in the
Garden? the flower, nettle, and the thorne the ſweet heathe and the
ſtincking weede, or the tilled lands with the buſhes, Briars or Brambles is
that the cauſe of theſe contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, nothing leſſe: All mankinds,
nature with ſinne is corrupted, and depraued in <hi>Adam,</hi> all things
there na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures change, mans heart of innocencie is nowe made nought, Gods
bleſſed earth before mans tranſgreſſion, now after his digreſſion
accurſed it is, with barrenneſſe bringing foorth vnprofitable fruites
ſuch as Nettle, Thornes, and Thiſtles and Bryars, to hinder the plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
groweth of any good, of which corrupt kind namely of bad: in each nature,
climate and quality, the worſer part exceedeth the beſt, more bad ground,
then good, more ſinners then Saints, more vitious then vertuous, there is in
the whole world a deludge of Iniquity, more prone, ſwifter running after all
manner of wickedneſſe to perpetrate them, then willing to performe any of
the leaſt Office, or intertaine ſuch motion inclining vnto God, or
goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18979:5"/>Princes in their Lawes and Courſes, imitate that
luſt One in Heauen: Iuſtice and Mercy kiſſe and méet each other:
Rewards they promiſe to the vertuous, and Threatening of Puniſhments to the
wicked: the one, to incourage in their way, the other, to deter, and retyre in
their way: experience how they are honoured and promoted, that are ſauoured
with integritie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of puniſhments, as Sword and Fire, that
to good are refractorie: yet will not God puniſh, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge, nor condemne,
but hee before viſites the ſinnes and offences of the people. The Kings
Maieſty imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates his God in this, whom he vnfainedly feareth and
ſerueth.</p>
            <p>This God on Earth, with the Sunne Moone, and States of Nobilitie,
Clergie, and Gentrie, his Court is centured, and gloriouſly adorned, and are
come to viſit and inquire.</p>
            <p>To iudge the cauſe, and diſcerne betwéene the people,
he appoints the reuerend Iudges, and ciuill Magiſtrats, to diſcerne and
ſearch into the Cauſe: and to the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, they call others to
teſtifie, in there Legall Procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that they will not in any the
leaſt manner be tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with iniuſtice, or wrong. The Fact, and Priſoner,
are produced, and publikely in Court read, Euidence of the matter of fact vpon
Oath ſworne, and bound at a day of appearance to iuſtifie the truth, and
nothing but the whole truth, as they would haue God to helpe them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="court_proceedings">
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:5"/>
            <head>THE MANNER OF THE Courts Proceedings.</head>
            <p>VPon the Oathes and deliberated inquiries of 15. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted honeſt
conſcionable men, now all Cauſes are begun to be conſulted of: and
leaſt they ſhould erre in the Termining, and yéelding of their
Verdict if ought they doubt, they addreſſe themſelues vnto the reuerend
Iudges, and Honourable Benchors, to be by them of their doubts reſolued, in
the matter informed, how to procéed iuſtly, truly, and conſcionable.
And that theſe thrée things ſhall concurre and agrée in their
procéedings, namely, iuſtly, truly and conſcionably, to inquire and
ſearch out the truth, they ſolemnly euery man take their Oathes on the holy
Euangeliſt, to the vttermoſt of their power ſo to doe: the accuſer is
ſent vp with the Bill of Indictment againſt the priſoner to them
preferred, Oath made of the manner of the Fact, wherein they cannot erre,
without wilfully they will. And behold the vigilant eye of Iuſtice! They haue
a Kéeper ſworne, to attend their going in, and commings forth, that
none ſhall heare their priuate conferrings. Where they ſit, none
appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that place, after teſtimonie giuen, that by this meanes, ſauour
and hatred may be layd aſide: if in one mans breſt, yet not in many: for
there are fifteene in number of them: and if that one will diſagree, they
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him, and chuſe another: And that there may not
<pb facs="tcp:18979:6"/> be the leaſt inuaſion, ſiniſter dealing, for
parſon, or pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uate cauſes, or reſpects, the Keeper that attendeth them,
is not to approch vnto them, vnleſſe they call him, nor to ſpeake with
them, except it vs to know whether they be agreed of their Verdict, or no, and
then to proclayme to the Court a Verdict, and to vſher them into the face of
the Court, there to manifeſt and declare what they haue done in thoſe
weighty matters committed to their truſt, iudgement, and conſcience.
Whoſe Names I haue here ſet downe.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Grand Inqueſt <hi>for London.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Greſham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Briſlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Allen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Riley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn May.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gutbert Haſelwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Gommerſall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Perkins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clement Pargiter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Checkley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Collet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Gatwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iames Ballard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Tilney.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:18979:6"/>
               <head>The Names of Middleſex Iury for the <hi>Queſt of
Inquirie.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Waterwoorth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis Marſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Gualter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Bates.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Chatfield.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicholas Day.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Faulkener.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Barnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Browne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Baker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Stanger.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis Andrewes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Monday.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward Saunders.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nathaniel Lomſden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Stanley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zacharie Howe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe by the Worſhipfull Bench, are told what a weightie
matter they are about, the peace and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of a King, and a whole
Kingdome, the honour and glorie of God, his Church, and Goſpell: they muſt
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the ſeditious diſturbers, and of the hurting, ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the
perſons, ſtealing their goods or chattels, if any
<pb facs="tcp:18979:7"/> ſuch Malefactors be brought before them, they all
ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muſt agrée, acquite, or condemne.</p>
            <p>And behold how God himſelfe approueth of what is done, by
reuealing moſt ſtrangely, as conſequently I will relate, on a ſudden
the ſecret lurking Malefactor, and the dubious hidden Truth: nay, in the end
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſay, both Iury and Iudges are cleare, and iuſt and vpright
in what they haue done, in their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
            <p>Iuſtice imitates God two manner of wayes in their Proceedings:
not raſhly doe they begin; but firſt, here is their preparation; (Inquirie)
whether the Crime bee ſo, or no; (iuſtly) whether there be cauſe or
matter to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, or ſpare; or the Originall whence the accuſation or
ſcandall ſhould tiſe: Reaſon, Conſcience, and Law, theſe are the
Guides and Lights to informe their Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, to ſpeake, to iudge, and
deeme of the Cauſe and Priſoner: (fairely) each party, the accuſed, and
accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, are face to face; where, what he can obiect, muſt be vpon Oath,
and the Priſoner, after ſuch teſtimonie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt him, is
ſuffered to ſpeake as much as hee can for himſelfe, and with patience
they heare him, and moſt temperately, modeſtly, mildly, and charitably, the
Iudge of the Court replyeth anſwere, according to the nature of their
Offence. Mercifully, <hi>lento pede,</hi> with God, ſlow to anger, ſorrie
for the Offences of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with temperate inuections: Witneſſe that
often <hi>Miſerere,</hi> which by heart is learned; for not a Letter of it,
one among a hundreth almoſt can truely tell: yet this mercifull warning they
vſe. And when Sentence is to procéede; from ſuch a Doue, Gall, from
ſuch ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, bitterneſſe: as the Lawes rigour,
Religious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, good Perſwaſions, by that Tongue vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and
vnfained Sorrow and Compaſſion, by watrie
<pb facs="tcp:18979:7"/> eyes expreſſed, and their Charitie ſhewed, in
preparing for diſtreſſed Soules, the Balme of <hi>Gilead:</hi> though
they wound, yet others to heale: and though they by the Law haue terrified
them, by the Sentence of Death, on theſe mortall Bodies, they comfort them
againe by that ſwéet heauenly Voyce of the Goſpell ſent from the
God aboue.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Iury of London <hi>for Life and
Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Patricke Powell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Lambe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Euerit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Higgins.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ralph Clarke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Latheman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Yorke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuel Bridges.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Withers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Smith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Hunter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Mallard.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:18979:8"/>
               <head>The Names of the Iury of Middleſex, <hi>for Life and
Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Eſtrey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Barret.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Burnet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Haward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Ewer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Halſey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Heerd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Bird.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Lifeild.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Winche.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Page.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Allen Parſons.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The tenour of theſe Iury mens Oathes, vpon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament
they doe proteſt, true, and truly to try, and true deliuerance make
betwéene out Soueraigne Lord the King, and the Priſoners at the Barre,
So helpe them God, and the Contents of that Booke. And the Fore-mans Oath they
ioyntly accept. And after ſuch Oath ſworne, the Indictment is read to them,
the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe produced, the Priſoner is brought forth to the Barre, in
their publike view, that they may ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, and as God directeth,
ſo they conclude. The Honourable and learned Benchers, whoſe Names are
ſubſcribed, if ought they doubt of, they are moſt willing
<pb facs="tcp:18979:8"/> to reſolue doubts, and to informe, that they may not
ere, and often times it falleth out that the Iury of life and death, acquites
them whom the Grand Inqueſt ſound before guilty.</p>
            <list>
               <head>THE NAMES OF THE HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Worſhipfull Benchers, and
Iuſtices in this Seſsions for the Citty of London, and County of
Middleſex.</head>
               <item>THe Right Honourable Sir <hi>William Cokayne</hi> Lord Mayor
of the Honourable Cittie of London, with diuers of the Aldermen his
Bretheren.</item>
               <item>The Honourable Sir <hi>Henry Mountague,</hi> Lord Chiefe
Iuſtice.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:18979:9"/>
               <head>Iuſtices for London.</head>
               <item>Sir Edward Sackucile.</item>
               <item>Maiſter Robert Heath Eſquier, Recorder.</item>
               <item>Sir Thomas Bennet</item>
               <item>Sir Thomas Lowe.</item>
               <item>Sir Thomas Middleton.</item>
               <item>Sir Iohn Iolles.</item>
               <item>Sir Iohn Lemon.</item>
               <item>Sir George Boules.</item>
               <item>Sir Iohn Bennet.</item>
               <item>Maiſter Thomas Iones Eſquier, common</item>
               <item>Seruient of the Cittie.</item>
               <item>Maiſter Robert Deane.</item>
               <item>Maiſter Ieames Cambell.</item>
               <item>Sheriffes of the Cittie of London.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Iuſtices for the Countie of Middleſex.</head>
               <item>Sir Thomas Fowler.</item>
               <item>Sir Baptiſt Hickes.</item>
               <item>Sir Allen Apſley, Lieutenant of the Tower of London.</item>
               <item>Sir Francis Dercy.</item>
               <item>Sir Henry Spiller, with diuers Iuſtices of the ſame
County, learned, and iudicious.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_accounts">
            <div type="trial">
               <pb facs="tcp:18979:9"/>
               <head>A true Relation of the Arraigning, Indicting and conuicting
of <hi>Andrew Ward,</hi> alias <hi>Alliar,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Percy:</hi> who
were both hanged at Tiburne on Monday, the 13. of December, 1619.</head>
               <p>IT is verified in theſe perſons, of whom I am now to relate
ſomewhat, that which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>That euill
ſhall hunt the wicked perſon, to ouerthrow him.</hi> Which in fine
happened, and befell to theſe; neuer leauing off to doe wickedly, as to worke
miſchiefe, till they were payd with that they had deſerued, which was
ſhame and confuſion. Shameleſſe were all their Facts and
Procéedings, without any humanitie, or feare of God, or Man, or
reſpect to Manhood: as their vſage manifeſted the ſame, towards thoſe
who fell into their hands, or ſtood at their mercy.</p>
               <p>Theſe two committed a Robbery vpon Hounſlaw Heath, vpon the
perſon of an Atturney, comming Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vp to London, to the Terme: they
tooke away all he had, ſtript him of all his apparrell, and put on him ſome
of their vile Clothes, and tooke his Shirt eff his back, and ſcoffingly
ſaid, That that Shirt was too fine for him, he ſhould haue another to keepe
him warme: and after this done, they bound him, and left him, and ſo
fled.</p>
               <p>Hauing ſo well ſped, they were fleſhed on for more ſuch
Booties, to meet withall, and to get ſuch Prizes, thence they coaſted
towards Royſton: and within a
<pb facs="tcp:18979:10"/> weeke after they robbed one a little on this ſide
Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, whom they bound, and tooke all that he had: the Rich and Captaine
Theefe cobbed, as they ſay, the poore Theefe: but ſomewhat they had, for
which they payd deare. A riding Cloake one of them had taken from the
Gentlemans Man: the which hee eſpyed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of their Backes, riding
towards Drury Lane: but their Iourney was ſtayed; They muſt leaue their
Turning, and keepe on ſtraight their way: which the Serieants will bring them
to; their Inne, and Place moſt fit for ſuch, euen Tiburne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trial">
               <head>A Relation why <hi>Thomas Horſey</hi> was hanged at
Smithfield Barres on Tueſday, the 14. of December, 1619.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Thomas Horſey</hi> had murthered out <hi>Elizabeth
Couer,</hi> dwelling in Turne-mill Street, in an Alley called <hi>Perſons
Alley.</hi> She was a Woman of a moſt lewd life, and they both vnlawfully
accompanied toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But ſo it fortuned, that ſuch loue which was
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, could not long continue, nor haue a happy Iſſue; but
Miſchiefe did attend them both likewiſe, as did the other two, formerly
treated of.</p>
               <p>Theſe two luſtie, luſtfull Louers, fell at variance
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, and ſuddenly hee ſlew her with a Pen-knife. After
the Fact committed, he fled, and got paſſage out of England, with Sir
<hi>Walter Rauleigh,</hi> late deceaſed, into (Guiana) where, and in ſome
other
<pb facs="tcp:18979:10"/> places, before he returned, he was abſent for the
terms of three yeares, after this Murther was by him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. In this
Proceſſe of time, hee thought none would haue knowne, or ſought after
him, to make him anſwere for the ſame, but that it had beene forgotten. At
his returne into England, he boldly repayred to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new his old acquaintance,
withſome others of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed friends faſhion, and by this meanes he
was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and apprehended.</p>
               <p>At his Arraignement he conidently and boldly deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Fact,
and ſaid another, who was in his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie did it, but not himſelfe: But at
his death, he freely confeſſed it, and ſaid, hee meant not to ſlay her,
but to giue her a marke, for remembrance of her abuſing of him: and his
concluſion concrning her, was, That he thought in his conſcience, through
her deſtruction, that many hundreds were
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aued from the Gallowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trial">
               <head>A true declaration of the manifold Facts done by <hi>Richard
Earper,</hi> who was executed on Monday laſt at Tiburne.</head>
               <p>AS Almighty God ouertooke others in their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, ſo
hee ſuddenly ſurpriſed him, as to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of many thouſands, hee
out of his owne mouth confeſſed, and ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Fact for which hee died, was for Robbing the houſe of Sir
<hi>Richard Sutton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Ofley,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18979:11"/> which houſe he Robbed once before this time, and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the Cuſhions which ſtood in the Windowes of Sir
<hi>Richard Suttons</hi> houſe hee had, and burnd them, and for the ſecond
time he Robd the houſe, he got into a Garden, and climed vp to a Window
wherein he entred, and tooke ſuch things, who pleaſed, and ſo came downe
the Staires of the ſame and got foorth. But marke how ſtrangely God
reueiled him, by a Dagger which he tooke of Sir <hi>Iohn Oflyes,</hi> he gaue
it to Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> Brother, of whom he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquired how he came by that
Dagger, who ſayd that <hi>Harper</hi> was the man that gaue it him, and ſo
there doubts were reſolued, that none but he could Rob that houſe: this
Arraingnement, he boldly denyed that fact, and all others of that nature: but
God who bringeth all things to light, reuealed at the laſt that he was, a
ſecret notorious Theefe, and Burglaer, as I will heereafter who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was by the Iury found guilty,
and adiudged by the Court to death and both Iuſtly, as himſelfe
confeſſed the day before his Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and at the time of his Execution.
The Euening before he ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>,
he diſgu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed him ſelfe
in Womans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell, and got away by water
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto the Banckes-ſide: but
God preuented him, and would not not let him ſo eſcape or flye vengeance,
for the Keeper ſoone ouertooke him.</p>
               <p>At the place of Execution he much bewailed his lewd life, and
declared that he had beene brought vp to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Tongue and Muſicke, but
ſuch was his moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked continued courſe of life, and ſayd that hee
was no ſooner entertained into a Seruice, but company and women withdrewe him
from thence, and counſelled him often to ſhifte. It was demaunded of him to
cleere his Conſcience, and to tell vnfainedly vnto the whole world whether
that woman with whom he accompanyed were his wife, or not? and he thus replyed
anſwere to them,
<pb facs="tcp:18979:11"/> 
                  <hi>God forgiue me for it, thou knoweſt that
ſhe is not.</hi> Hee laſtly confeſſed, that hee had vſed to robbe the
Court ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, and that he had ſtolne twiſe the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
cuſhions from his Chaire of State, and that Suite which was of an
Orrange-tawny-colour broad-cloth, he ſtole out of the Spicery, with a
Fetherbed.</p>
               <p>For theſe his moſt fowle and vile offence, he wept moſt
bitterly, and prayed heartily vnto GOD for pardon and remiſſion: vnto
whoſe vnexpreſſable mercie, I muſt leaue him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trial">
               <p>At this Seſſions was arraigned and executed at Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne
<hi>Thomas Porter</hi> a Brewer by Trade, who in play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Cards with one
<hi>Chriſtopher Body,</hi> a Player, fell out with him, who ſo prouoked
him, that hee tooke a Nowle, that lay on the Boarde, and thruſt it into his
ſide, of which mortall wound he dyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trial">
               <p>At this Seſſions were conuicted and executed vppon the
ſtatute of Vagrancie, <hi>Samuell Prat,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Smith,</hi> both
which the Statute adiudged to be Fellons, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any benefite of Cleargie,
hauing béene before whipt, and burnt in the Shoulder, with a Romane
<hi>R.</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning backe with their Paſſes, they were both
adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to dye: and the one was hanged at White Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and the other at
Grayes Inne Lane ende.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:18979:12"/>
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THus Life is deſtroyed by Life, and Earth turnes Earth to
Earth. The Life of the Law, which is iuſt, takes away the Life of the lewd,
and vniuſt. Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Men made of Earth, turnes theſe miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
vnto the Graue, Duſt, and Earth. But Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie requires of mee to
lodge this hope in my breaſt, That he who came downe from Heauen to Earth, to
bring vs vnto euerlaſting Life, though Death and Graue haue now ſwallowed
them vp, and gotten the victorie of them; yet by vertue of his moſt powerfull
Conqueſt, and glorious Reſurrection, they ſhall riſe out of the duſt
of their Graues; for their Corruption, then to put on Incorruption, for their
Mortall and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie Life, an Immortall and euerlaſting Life: Which
Lord Ieſus graunt vnto vs all, in thy appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18979:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
